so we want to welcome our guest John
Kaku back to the show John joined us on
two previous newsbeat episodes one about
the US government's war on the press and
the other about former CIA director Gina
haspel operating a black site and
destroying evidence and as rashed
reminded us we actually go back much
further W about 10 years now um when we
were back at an ALT weekly uh together
way back in the day um so for listeners
who may not know John's a former C
analyst and case officer former senior
investigator for the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee and former
counterterrorism consultant while at the
CIA he conducted critical
counterterrorism missions overseas
following the September 11th terrorist
attacks and refused to be trained in
so-called enhanced interrogation
techniques something we'll get to in a
few more moments after leaving the CIA
he appeared on ABC News and confirmed
that the agency water boarded detainees
which is torture he also revealed that
this practice was not just the result of
a few Rogue agents but official US
policy sanction at the highest levels of
the government he was indicted by the
Obama Administration under the Espionage
Act a law designed to punish spies and
served 30 months in prison as a result
of those
Revelations John's the sole CIA agent to
go to jail in connection with the US
torture program despite the fact he
never tortured anyone rather he blew the
whistle on
it he currently writes about National
Security intelligence Foreign Affairs
and much more on his loud and clear
substack and co-host the daily radio
show on podcast political Misfits hell
of a resume uh so John welcome back to
the show thank you so much good to see
you both and uh what I'd like to do uh
for listeners right off the bat is to is
to uh is to talk about that Journey we
just outlined so if you could paint us a
portrait of what it means to be a
whistleblower share if you possibly can
you know what this what this whole
ordeal has been like personally
professionally you risked your life for
this country and then after exposing
something internationally recognized as
a crime against humanity torture you're
indicted as a spy um so if you could you
know please describe the Fallout the
toll it took on you and your family and
we're curious given all that's happened
if you had the choice
would you do it all
again I I'll answer that part first
that's the easy one the answer is yes
100% yes 1,00% yes I'd do it today today
I've I've realized that that this this
sort of is my purpose in life and uh
somebody had to say something I'm glad
that it was me the more difficult answer
is it's not just what what I experienced
as a whistleblower it's what any whistle
blower experiences especially a national
security
whistleblower you know we have a we have
a law in this country called The
Whistleblower protection act which
specifically exempts National Security
whistleblowers from its
protections and so if you blow the
whistle on waste fraud abuse illegality
or threats to the public health or
Public Safety which is the legal
definition of
whistleblowing and you work for the CIA
the FBI NSA DOD the White House
or even the Department of Homeland
Security you're probably going to go to
prison and not just prison you're
probably going to be indicted under the
Espionage Act I'll get to that in a
second because it's really
important beyond
that you're going to be shocked at how
many friends in some cases lifelong
friends will walk away from you and
never speak to you again you're going to
be shocked that the marriage that you
thought was so rock solid turns out to
not be so Rock Solid not when you know
your wife is a senior Cia officer and is
concerned about her own
career uh you're going to be
shocked at how quickly bankruptcy is
upon you which is the government's plan
they do something called they do two
things called venue shopping and charge
stacking venue shopping is that they
will seek to indict you in the federal
district
court that where they are they are
confident you will get a guilty verdict
and the longest possible
sentence in my case and in the case of
other National Security whistleblowers
that's the eastern district of
Virginia where no National Security
defendant has ever won a case there
ever
um and then you have to start thinking
about
the definition of
Espionage the Espionage Act was written
in
1917 to combat German savitur during the
first world war it has never been
meaningfully updated and in fact the SPN
act doesn't even mention classified
information it mentions only what it
calls National Defense information and
then doesn't Define what that
means so the
secret that you're charged with
exposing is whatever the justice
department says it is whether it's
actually secret or not in my case my
case set a very
dangerous precedent or two I had a
hanging judge by the name of Leoni
brinka she was a Ronald Reagan is a
Ronald Reagan
appointee and um she reserved most
national security cases for herself she
did my case she did uh Jeffrey
Sterling's case she did Zacharias musawi
she uh had the Ed Snowden case which is
still open and hanging over his head uh
she had originally been assigned the
Julian Assange case so she keeps all
these cases for
herself and
um in my case
um I clearly had no Criminal Intent and
um and the justice department admitted
in court that I had no Criminal
Intent and so my lawyer said well your
honor you know Tom Drake the NSA
whistleblower he was in the district of
Maryland no Criminal Intent all those
charges fell apart they were thrown out
she says I am electing to not respect
that
decision and if you don't like it you
can go to the Circuit the fourth Circuit
Court of Appeals which of course you do
Post conviction and post
incarceration and I remember my lawyer
standing up and saying your honor are
are you saying that a person can
accidentally commit
Espionage and she said that's exactly
what I'm saying and she looked at me and
she said Mr
kiraku either you did it or you didn't
do it and I think you did
it so we walked out of court and as we
were walking out I said to my
lawyers I should add that we had made
110 motions for the declassification of
documents that I needed to to uh uh uh
defend myself and we had we had blocked
out two days for arguments on these 110
motions and she said I'm going to deny
all 110 of these motions all all 110 you
don't get anything so I couldn't defend
myself so we're walking out of court and
I said to my lawyers A-list lawyers some
of the best lawyers in America I said
what just
happened and one of my attorneys said
we just lost the case that's what
happened well this was like the first
hearing we we have a Year's worth of
hearings ahead of us which we would lose
at every step of the way now I was
charged with five felonies including
three counts of Espionage of course I
hadn't committed
Espionage and so what the justice
department did was um they charged me
they waited till I went bankrupt and
then they dropped the charges and one
other thing you The Limited discovery
that we did
get there was a memo from John Brennan
who became the CIA director at the time
was the
uh was the deputy National Security
adviser for counterterrorism John and I
always hated each other we went back 30
years and um there's a memo from Brennan
to Eric Holder the attorney general and
he says charge him with
Espionage and holder rates back and says
my people don't think he committed
Espionage and then Brennan wrote back
and said charge him any way and make him
defend
himself and that's what they did and
then when I went
bankrupt uh they they dropped the
charges it's incredible John thanks for
thanks for sharing that I and I know
even today all these years later it's
still very emotional probably difficult
for you to to relive so we do appreciate
it um just really quick before we get
into the question some some of our other
questions including about Julian Assange
one of the things that I still can't
believe about the Espionage Act is that
it it is one of the most undemocratic
laws that we have on the books and one
of Edward snowden's Arguments for not
wanting to actually come back to face
trial is because you are not afforded as
you know a public interest defense um so
I I I I think this is this is important
for listeners can you explain to people
the undemocratic nature of this and why
a public interest defense would be so
helpful for people like yourself or the
Snowden or Assange if he was actually
going to you know um face prosecution
rather than take a guilty ple why that's
so important uh that is such an
important question um there is no
affirmative defense in the ESPN act and
courts over the last century have ruled
that people cannot get up in court and
say I did it but I did it in the public
interest let me explain you can't
explain
as judge uh brinka said you either did
it or you didn't do it Ed Snowden I've
talked to Ed about this at length
and he told me from the very beginning
that he was willing to come home and he
was willing to go to
prison if he could get up in court and
explain that what he did was in the
interest of the American
people and so he hired my attorneys I I
said I have the best attorneys in
America you got to hire these guys they
they only do white color defense and
National Security so he hired my
lawyers and they began engaging the
justice department
in conversations very preliminary
conversations now Ed told me on the QT
he was willing to go to prison for 10
years 20 years whatever it took he knew
what he was getting into and he did it
for the public
interest so when the lawyers went to the
justice department said look he's
willing to come home and mind you this
is you know 11 years ago he's willing to
come home but he wants he wants to make
a statement in court they said
absolutely
not so let me ask
then if you're a prosecutor at the
justice department or you're an FBI
agent in The Counter Intelligence
Division isn't it important to you to
take custody of this man who you have
called the most d dangerous man in
America because he's offering to deliver
himself to you all he wants to do is to
explain his actions and they said
absolutely
not and so they never got
him so yes you know over the over the
years over the century the last century
the the uh Espino act has been used to
imprison Eugene V Debs popular
presidential candidate uh a Hollywood
producer who who produced a movie that
was deemed to be not pro British enough
and then ended up getting like a decade
in
prison uh and and one other thing and I
apologize in advance for throwing a a
number at you
but but between the creation the the
founding of the Espionage Act and the
election of Barack
Obama three people three Americans were
charged with Espionage for speaking to
the Press just under Obama eight of us
were charged with Espionage for speaking
to the Press not for spying for other
countries not for taking money for
sensitive information but for going to
the media and saying the American
government is committing war crimes and
here are the
details that's what gets you locked up
yep it's incredible and So speaking of
locked up while not in the US but um in
self-imposed imprisonment at at the
Ecuadorian EMB Embassy in the UK and
then also in a UK prison um as he
awaited an extradition hearing Julian
Assange obviously um a few weeks ago
accepted a guilty play in his Espionage
Act case which I still can't believe was
brought because under the Obama
Administration which obviously Biden
played a huge hand in uh that doj which
was aggressive against everybody
including yourself um decided they
couldn't bring charges against Assange
they had a quote New York times problem
if they did yet Trump Administration
does it Biden continues with the
prosecution and he takes his guilty
plate and Chris and I were sort of
stunned with the um the way that this
was being discussed yes it was great to
us that Assange was finally being
released he go back to his family it's a
win for him especially because of his
physical um mental and his health
conditions just overall yet the
government still in our view got a guilt
a conviction essentially under the ESP
act for a publisher a journalist setting
a hugely a dangerous precedent that will
live on forever we can never go back um
from that we'll never return from that
so well there's disagreement about that
sure um that was my my position was the
same as yours yeah I was gonna ask you
what your position was John because I
know there's disagreement but I'm just
wondering what your position is and if
you want to bring up what you know what
other people say about that that notion
that a guilty plea is different than a a
conviction and it's not a precedent
and and that's really it I was talking
to chip Gibbons about this the other day
uh chip is a is a great he's an attorney
and a great champion of of not just
civil liberties but also of the
scrapping and rewriting of the uh
Espionage Act and I expressed exactly
the same concerns that you just
expressed and he said well not
necessarily first of
all um even though it technically falls
under the Espionage Act he didn't plead
guilty to espionage he plad guilty to
conspiracy to commit ESP
okay well all right I'm not a lawyer
what do I know but he said because it
was a plea deal future prosecutors can't
use it to Leverage The indictment of
another
journalist and I said okay well all
right I get that too but let me give you
some background that I think you'll have
fun with I
um I am a very proud longtime supporter
of both Julian Assange and wikileak
and
um and I made three trips to Iceland to
meet with Wikileaks uh in December
January and and February this
year to
strategize uh with attorneys and and
activists and journalists we were all
expecting that Julian would be would be
extradited to uh to the eastern district
of Virginia and face trial there now
Julian also had some of the best legal
Minds that money could buy on the
payroll in in the form of Barry Pollock
here in the in in Washington Barry's
legendary and
um and Barry never gave up hope because
he knew that he had the facts on his
side he also knew
that public opinion plays at least as
great a role in in people's
convictions as the facts
do and the biggest problem that Julian
had was that almost everybody who
considers himself or herself to be a
Democrat blames Julian Assange for
giving us Donald
Trump right and they were just convinced
that he wasn't going to get a fair trial
it just wasn't possible to get a fair
trial Julian also didn't trust the
justice department to
um to uh respect the agreement and
that's why see there was they were at
logger heads for a long time because
Justice
insisted that Julian be brought to
Alexandria
Virginia um that he take the plea in the
eastern district of Virginia and then be
expelled to Australia and he said no he
said I don't believe them I don't trust
them and if they lock me up I'm going to
kill myself and so the deal that Barry
Pollock was able to negotiate was that
they
process him in the federal district that
is closest physically closest to
Australia and that
was sipan Northern Mariana Islands I had
no idea there was a federal court there
seriously and it all worked out you know
there was one odd provision and it was
funny because the justice department
just cackled with the light that it was
this great victory for them and it made
me laugh that they're just such idiots
um part of the the agreement
was that he had to promise not to
publish any unpublished material that
originated with Chelsea
Manning and he had to swear out an
affidavit saying that he didn't have any
and that Wikileaks had to purge from its
systems any unpublished material from
Chelsea Lan well there is no unpublished
material from Chelsea
Manning now
interestingly the CIA didn't demand that
any about Vault 7 and Vault 8 needed to
be
purged or anything about Russian troll
Farms that Wikileaks has exposed or the
Church of
Scientology that's on the website you
know people think oh well you know
Wikileaks it's a Russian front
organization and uh Julian Assan she's a
Russian agent and all they do is they
try to uncover American Secrets people
who say that have never been to the
Wikileaks
website they've never looked to see what
it is that leaks is revealing because
they
reveal protected information from all
around the world in the public
interest you know I'm I'm I'm thrilled
that Julian is free that was the goal
and I don't care so much about a
conspiracy charge and he's he's banned
from applying for an American green card
for 25 years it's like great that's
great great punishment um but the
important the suggestion that they they
don't produce or reproduce anything in
their possession as a journalistic
outfit to me is also insulting but you
know it is it's insulting that's right
but I'm glad he's home with his wife and
his kids and you know his mom his dad
his
brother it's it's better this way John
you know just on the topic of Julian and
yourself you know again back to just the
whole whistleblower being a
whistleblower you know I mean all the
things that that Assan has exposed um
all the things that you've exposed um if
we could talk a little bit about just
how frustrating is it for you uh that in
your case you know they went after you
yet the people who were actually
committing the crimes yeah
um weren't even pursued and in fact
we're celebrated in some cases we
mentioned Gina haspel at the at at the
top of the episode here who are some of
the people that it just still sits with
you like those are the people who should
have been held accountable
yeah wow let's make a list number one is
Jose
Rodriguez the former deputy director for
operations at the CIA the former
director of the of the uh
counterterrorism Center and Gina
haspel's uh boss and uh and Rabbi at the
CIA it
was it was Jose who implemented
the torture program it was Jose who
ordered the training for the torturers
and then when word started getting out
it was Jose who ordered that the tapes
of the torture sessions be destroyed
after being specifically told by the
White House Council don't destroy the
tapes and not only did he destroy
them I mean it's not like he put them on
a magnet or something he had them thrown
into an industrial grinder so that they
were pulverized and couldn't possibly
be
recovered so my own personal view is
that Jose is a a war
criminal and should face International
charges uh there are several people
whose names you wouldn't recognize
around Jose whose careers rose with
Jose's who should be in the same dock in
the ha uh Jim pavit the former deputy
director of the CIA for uh for
operations uh died a year and a half ago
he should have been in the dock uh
George tennet listen George is a nice
guy right great hero of the Greek
American Community but George is a war
criminal uh what did he get he got a $6
million book advance and a position on
the board of directors of a of a vulture
Fund in New York City he has more money
than he could possibly count in a
lifetime so yeah I was angry about about
a lot of that for a long time but you
know after a period of time you you come
to the real
ization
that you're right and they're wrong
right I can sleep at night my kids are
proud of me I like the person that I am
and I know that history will smile on me
you know when I'm dead and gone and
people are studying this period you know
in December of 2014 I was still in
prison I had about six weeks to go and I
called my wife I was allowed to call her
for 15 minutes every other
day and I said hey how's your
day she said it's great and I said
really great why is it
great and she said because the Senate
torture report was released today and it
proved that everything you said was true
she said John McCain got up on the floor
of the Senate and said you were an
American hero and that the American
people would never have known
what the US government was doing in
their name had you not told them it was
worth it and it was it was worth it so
you know the likes of Jose they can have
their little retirement homes in St
Augustine Florida I don't
care I can sleep at night and know that
I'm not a war criminal with the blood of
hundreds or perhaps thousands of people
on my hands yeah definitely and John the
uh you know we like to continuously
bring up these stories because you know
the war and terror is still going on
we're still this surveillance state is
still being expanded and heavily funded
um they're finding new ways to find way
you know to to surveil American citizens
and people abroad um you mentioned the
Senate torture report I spoke uh we
briefly spoke to you yesterday and I
talked about how that was the first
story I wrote about you back in December
2014 when that was released because
because the torture report was heavily
uh reliant on the story of Abu zubeda
who was accused of being in I think the
third ranking member of aleda which if
I'm right but then they yes years later
they basically retracted that um wasn't
true yep and he's being held in
Guantanamo still um there's an update to
his case um and if I remember correctly
I believe that you were not only part of
the operation that led to his capture in
Pakistan um but you also either
interviewed him or you were with him
after the capture if I maybe I hope I
have those correct I I led the capture
and then I sat with him for 56 hours
after he was captured yeah so I bring
this up because he is petitioning to be
released by a mil I think a military
review board and I don't I don't know if
that if there's been an update on that
case I'm assuming you've been following
it um I bring him up because he's
basically exemplifies all that's gone
wrong um since then he was the first
person to be um waterboarded uh and some
of these torture techniques used against
him effectively a guinea pig um he was
rendered thrown in Guantanamo um to to
the American public you bring up you
know maybe some people don't know him
other people's he's just like scum of
the earth because they think he was
involved um um can you just if you have
any update on on zubeda's case do you
mind mentioning that and can you just
just um sort of talk about him as sort
of like the example of of everything
that sort of went wrong at that in that
period
sure I and I do have an update
um so in December of 2002 I was the
chief of counterterrorism operations in
Pakistan for the CIA and we got word
that Abu zua was somewhere in Pakistan
we had to take him alive he was
identified to us as the number three in
al-Qaeda I'm going to make a very very
long story very short and say number one
he was not the number three in al-Qaeda
he was never even a member of al-Qaeda
he was a bad guy he um created uh uh
founded al-qaeda's Safe House in Pasha
Pakistan the House Of Martyrs he founded
al-qaeda's two training camps in
southern Afghanistan in helmond and um
and uh kahar provinces and he acted as
something of a of a
logistician if you wanted to go to
Afghanistan fight he would get you
across the border if you were tired of
the fight and wanted to go home he would
get a false passport and a plane ticket
and send you home um but he had never
joined Al-Qaeda he was not the number
three in al-Qaeda he had never pledged
fty to Usama Bin Laden and he had
literally nothing to do with 911
nothing but we tortured him
mercilessly in violation of both us and
International law he was held at a
series of six secret prisons all around
the world where he was tortured at black
sites and then finally sent to
Guantanamo and even
after the the
government reluctantly admitted ah he
really wasn't the number three in
al-Qaeda they still didn't want to let
him go why because he knew too much
about CIA
methods right the act of torture was
classified currently and properly
classified is the is the phrase that the
CIA uses all the time even his drawings
he drew sketches of himself being
tortured those were
classified and kept from the
public so Abu zubeda has been in
American custody since March 28th 2002
that's a long time a long time he was a
kid when I captured him now he's on the
back end of middle age and he's never
been charged with a crime well the
Constitution says we all have a right to
face a a jury of our peers and to face
our accusers in a court of law he's
never been given those rights and so my
mantra for years has
been that he must be released he must be
released and I've gone so far as to go
on to Twitter and to apologize because I
know that the government won't so I
apologize to him sort of In Absentia for
this illegal and inhuman and immoral
treatment now with that said I spoke to
his lead attorney a week
ago and uh and he said a couple of funny
things he said something that really
made me feel great he said that when I
went
public in
2007 word immediately got
around the prisoners at Al-Qaeda that a
CIA man had confirmed what they had been
alleging they said a friendly guard told
them that I had blown the whistle on the
torture program he said it was like
giving them New
Life uh that made me very
happy the lawyer also
said that ABA has some different
Recollections of our en counter that
night back in
um but that he looks forward to the two
of us having dinner together as freem
men and that also means a lot you know
the the media have made a great deal
about well you know could he
be expelled to Saudi Arabia he's
Palestinian but he was born in Saudi
Arabia well he couldn't be expelled to
Saudi Arabia or to Yemen or that's not
the way these things work these releases
you know over the years we've
released hundreds of prisoners from
Guantanamo almost all of whom have been
innocent of any
crime
and if they can go back to their country
they go back to their country but in the
case of abua he has no
country and so what we've done with
other Palestinians or with prisoners who
can't be returned to their home
countries because it would be too
dangerous for them there they would be
tortured Ed or killed or harassed or you
know the intelligence service would be
on
them they go to places like Tahiti
Albania
Switzerland uh Biz Costa
Rica uh
Thailand so what's happening
now is there are dual negotiations
underway number
one is between aba's legal team and the
justice department where they're looking
for some crime that he can plead guilty
to right conspiracy to provide material
support to terrorism I'm just making
that up
something so that he'll plead guilty
he'll be found guilty sentenced to time
served and
expelled the second negotiation is with
a wide variety of countries with the
wherewithal to be able to handle
somebody who's as high
high-profile as abuaba is abua probably
can't go to a place like bise because
the bans they I
mean I don't even know how many people
there are in bise let alone how many
people in the National Police or the
intelligence
service but if he could go to someplace
like Muhammad udah for example is is now
uh in the
Netherlands uh or there are prisoners in
former prisoners in Italy
who have been welcomed Switzerland as I
said so if if they can negotiate The
Plea and negotiate a relocation package
this thing might actually come to an end
thank
god oh you know what let me add one more
thought one of the important things
about the Senate torture
report which was actually not really the
Senate torture report it's a heavily
reacted 500 page executive summary of
the 5,000 page Senate torture report one
of the important things is in the
footnotes right so it's very heavily
redacted to really understand what the
CIA did to these people you have to read
the footnotes and there's there's a
footnote there that I've quoted many
times in my own writing where the CIA
said that Abu zua would never be
released under any circumstances
he would never be permitted to um
communicate with the outside
world and when he died at Guantanamo he
was to be cremated and his ashes cast
into the
Caribbean that's not the cia's decision
to
make the CIA is not a law enforcement
organization it's not up to them to make
that call and so it looks like maybe
after all these years the government is
finally coming to the realization we
need to end this thing my God that's
incredible terrible yeah horrific um
speaking of horrific and and just more
you know indefinite detention and
torture um we're curious to get your
thoughts on these latest reports um
coming out of the conflict um with
Israel uh regarding these makeshift sort
of detainment camps and prisons um CNN
had a report recently where a
whistleblower Israeli whistleblower um
leaked details of forced
amputations um women and children being
held there there's reports of mass rapes
sexual abuse um we spoke with um former
DOD official uh Mark Fallon a couple
weeks ago just in the context of of you
know Israel has has stated you know this
is they're they're taking this as the
October 7th attacks is there sort of
9911 um and and he you know warned about
the proliferation of of sort of more
enemies and combatants regarding their
response um so what's your what's your
thoughts on this what specifically about
these these torture camps that are that
are coming out yeah uh allegedly there's
the number I I had seen was over 10,000
potential prisoners there um and what
needs to be done I saw that number too
first of all let me say if Mark Fallon
says it you can believe
it um he's he's a great truth tell and
um I've heard the same
reports um there are doctors reporting
back to the United Nations on the
inordinate number of amputations that
are taking place um among Palestinian
prisoners uh unnecessary amputations
because if you cut off their legs they
can't run after you with a you know a
bomb strap to them right or you cut off
their arms they can't find they can't
fire a gun I mean the most grotesque
human rights violations
imaginable and it's even worse than that
I spoke to an Israeli uh human rights
attorney two or three weeks
ago who who represents only Palestinians
in Israeli prisons and he said as soon
as October 7th took place the entire
Israeli prison system enacted a new uh
regulation that Palestinians who are
incarcerated are not permitted to
walk meaning to get from point A to
point B you have to crawl on your hands
and knees you want to go to the
cafeteria crawl on on your hands and
knees he said you can do that for 10
minutes you can't do it for a year and a
half and if you object if you speak in
more than a whisper you're beaten with a
truncheon or a piece of rebar they'll
break your legs they'll break your arms
and then God forbid they'll amputate
them because they become
infected so I think this is an
absolutely hideous human rights ongoing
human rights
violation that the entire world is
overlooking they're choosing to overlook
and criminally the US government has
elected to just pretend it's not
happening yeah John so um we we went
back just to see what you what you have
going on and as as Chris mentioned up
top it's it's a lot um but you did
report on an interesting story that I
wasn't even aware of and I think
everybody would find interesting I I I
couldn't believe it um you reported on
the National Archives um which is
obviously has to protect founding
documents and plays an instrum
instrumental role in declassification
but you found out that's really that's
not been the cas in recent years partly
due to defunding and partly due to what
seems like just like they don't want to
do it really they don't want to actually
um perform their function um can you
tell listeners about the story with the
National Archives I mean we're laughing
but it is a it is a serious
story you know honest to God I forgot I
wrote that until you just mentioned it
uh yeah this is a serious story so the
National Archives of course is the is
the ultimate repository of literally
every document that's produced by a US
government employee
right especially classified documents
now we have a mandatory declassification
law in this country that says that every
document should be Declassified after 30
or 35 years it's called statutory
declassification the thing is is you
need a human being to actually read it
after 30 or 35 years to say okay yeah
this stuff isn't still classified
so um it should be we can declassify it
and put it on the
website but the problems are
several number
one archives is using a computer system
that's 20 years old it's just not
updated number two the head of archives
has asked for a smaller fed federal
budget who does that like ever in the
history of America like you know what my
agent needs less money next year and so
year after year after year after year
there's no computer
upgrade number three that computer
system has no connectivity with any
other governmental
organization because it's so many
generations behind the times so if
somebody from the state
department says oh you know we've got
these documents we're going to send them
over to you they have to like physically
Al put them in the mail and double wrap
them and send them hard copy to the
National Archives because there's no
internet
connectivity and number four and this is
the worst part of it because of all
these problems there's something like a
500e wait for the Fulfillment of Freedom
of Information Act
requests it's like you can file a
Freedom of Information Act request and
the law says that they have 30 days to
tell you that they've received your
request and then they have 90 days to
answer the
request but there's a 500e wait because
there's just nobody to actually do the
work it it just doesn't exist I'll give
you just one typical
example um in
2015 I wanted to write an article about
a guy popular science fiction writer
from the
1950s who may may have worked for NSA he
may have worked for CIA um but all the
while was writing these Hollywood you
know B
movies uh under a pseudonym so I said
here the guy's dead here's his name
here's a copy of his death certificate
and I would just like to know was he a
CIA or NSA employee between 1950 and
1954 and if so you know please tell me
about his
career so I got a letter back I got an
email back uh also in
2015 saying that um they had received
the
request that was nine years ago I never
heard anything again and so I wrote an
email to the CIA a year ago and I said
hey you guys ignored this request you
had 180 days or or 90 days to respond to
it and here we it's N9 years later I
have now resp response and they said oh
you are in the line to be answered but
at the current rate it's going to be
about 30 more years and and you know
what you say well you guys are violating
the law and they say call your
Congressman you know I mean I mean John
I mean just hearing that right I mean
how convenient for them right I mean you
gotta oh sure I'm not I'm not trying to
be conspiratorial here but it's like you
know it's like is it is it just laps of
you know funding and Mis and gross
mismag or is that just deliberately so
they don't have to fulfill these
requests I mean it's incredible I I'll
tell you another quick story when when I
was an analyst I was like a mid-career
analyst and I was asked to be the acting
Deputy National Intelligence officer for
the Middle East right it's kind of a big
deal it's it's handling the Middle East
for the
entire uh intelligence community and I
did this for six weeks it was a six-
week rotation so I go up up there uh
it's on the seventh floor of the CIA the
the executive floor and I was all
gung-ho you know I'm going to write a
paper about Saddam Hussein I'm going to
write a paper about you know
whatever and they said no we want you to
work on these Freedom of Information Act
requests so just go through uh these
documents and black out everything
that's classified well the stack of
documents was literally eight feet tall
and this was just for this one National
Intelligence officer for the Middle East
it was 8 feet tall I worked 12-hour days
six days a week for the entirety of that
six weeks to go through every one of
those documents and say these are old
they're historical they're not important
nobody cares about the Suez Crisis and
what you know John Foster dullus said to
his brother about the Suez Crisis it's
all for the
historians so almost none of it was
classified and then the nio
said you saved me 10 years worth of
work and I said but I mean there there
shouldn't be any backlog for Foya we
should have an army of Foya people hire
retirees to come in and just get the the
American people own this information
they should have access to it Scholars
should have ready access to it and
nobody does incredible but if you you
want to give the filmmakers behind Zero
Dark 30 oh behind the scenes don't get
me started just just speak to your
favorite uh national security officer
that's right and there will be no
implications for that and if you're a
CIA analyst you get a Rolex and tickets
to the premiere in
exchange yeah nice it's incredible um
John I mean yeah it's always a pleasure
to speak with you we always appreciate
the time that you you give us I know
you're a busy busy person uh you know we
can speak to you we can speak to you for
hours on any range of in issues that
come up um thanks for your good
questions thank you you know it's it's
always great so we really appreciate you
taking some time out and doing this with
us thanks for having me good to see you
both